<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-28T22:12:36-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ixchel González Ramírez</title><subtitle>My academic webpage</subtitle><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><entry><title type="html">A California Native Plant Society public hike: learning little plants among the redwoods</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/CNPS_bryowalk" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A California Native Plant Society public hike: learning little plants among the redwoods" /><published>2025-04-02T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/CNPS_bryowalk</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/CNPS_bryowalk"><![CDATA[<p>*Main post picture by Sunit Mody</p>

<p>On March 16th, a group of ~25 enthusiastic people joined me on a “hike” (one could call it a walk, others would fairly refer to it as a crawl) in Reinhardt Redwoods Regional park to look at the microworld that lives among the redwoods. 
After what I hope was a short but encouraging talk about <em>all the reasons why bryophytes are so cool</em>, we started by checking out the first division of bryophytes, hornworts, that grow on the side of the trails. This year they were very happy with the rain, and thriving, already showing off their horns. 
We then moved to a slightly drier environment, just in a little exposed area besides the trail where more xerophytic and ephemeral bryophytes grow. The battle to avoid poison oak was extremely worth it because we were able to see a very healthy population of <em>Fossombronia</em> producing its characteristic very rounded sporangia on top of a hyaline stalk. Living together with <em>Fossombronia</em>, we found many <em>Riccia</em>! Too young to see the spores, but definitively thriving. I wish I had taken a picture of the group kneeling and getting their face close to the ground to appreciate these endearing plants, but I was too busy joining them in the crawling activity.</p>

<p><img src="images/bryo_walk/showing_fossombronia.png" alt="Showing Fossombronia and Riccia" width="550" />
<em>Fossombronia and Riccia, two species that thrive as ephemerals! While bryophytes are commonly thought to be found only in very wet areas, some species are adapted to drier environments and perform very important ecosystem services, for example “nourishing” and preserving the soil. Picture by Kevin Dixon</em></p>

<p>We then took some time to observe very closely the bark of the trees, and we discussed how to distinguish leafy liverworts from mosses, and very wet lichens from liverworts.</p>

<p>Finally, we proceded to walk more than 200m without stopping (quite the achievement for a group of bryologists!) to find ourselves under the canopy of the redwoods, where we observed one of the most especial liverworts (in my controversial opinion) of this state park: <em>Cryptomitrium tenerum</em>. While we were at it, a few people made my day by taking interest on plants life cycle!!! They indulge me by letting me rant about alternation of generations for more than 10 min, and we even saw some fern gametophytes!</p>

<p><img src="images/bryo_walk/Cryptomitrium.png" alt="Cryptomitrium_tenerum" width="550" />
<em>Cryptomitrium tenerum, a complex thalloid liverwort who is the only representative of its genus in Northamerica. It likes shaded and wet environments, just like the one the redwoods provide! Picture by Edy H.</em></p>

<p>But little we knew that the star of the day was going to be at the very end of our hike. Just when I was about to give up on our quest for the bottle liverwort, a tenacious attendant spotted them by a barbecue pit!</p>

<p><img src="images/bryo_walk/Sphaerocarpos.png" alt="Sphaerocarpos_texanus" width="550" />
<em>Sphaerocarpos texanus, the bottle liverwort spotted at the very end of our hike. Picture by Sunit Mody</em></p>

<p><strong>Thank you so so much to all the attendants to this hike!</strong> Your interest, curiosity, and energy was inspiring! I hope you found it entertaining and above all I hope you left with an appretiation and curiosity for the little things that we don’t always look at, yet they are always there, ready to amaze us if we give them the chance!
Thank you so much to CNPS-East Bay Chapter, especially to Sally, for organizing this event!</p>]]></content><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Main post picture by Sunit Mody]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/bryo_hike.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/bryo_hike.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New pre-print on the microbiome of C. californica</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/microbiome" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New pre-print on the microbiome of C. californica" /><published>2025-01-25T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-25T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/microbiome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/microbiome"><![CDATA[<p>In collaboration with my friend and colleague <a href="https://michaelsongagradstudent.github.io">Mick Song</a>, we used the sequencing of field collected liverworts in the species <em>C. californica</em> to study their associated microbiome. In this fun collaboration we learned that there is a core group of bacteria that is present across all samples. We also found that the differences observed in the composition is better explained by the genetics of the host liverwort. All of this opens interesting question about the role that liverworts might play in a selection mechanism of the bacteria in their microbiome.</p>

<p>Read our pre-print <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2025.01.23.634585v1">HERE</a></p>]]></content><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><category term="news" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In collaboration with my friend and colleague Mick Song, we used the sequencing of field collected liverworts in the species C. californica to study their associated microbiome. In this fun collaboration we learned that there is a core group of bacteria that is present across all samples. We also found that the differences observed in the composition is better explained by the genetics of the host liverwort. All of this opens interesting question about the role that liverworts might play in a selection mechanism of the bacteria in their microbiome.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/microbiome.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/microbiome.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Morphology, function, and evolution of liverwort scales</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/liverwort-scales" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Morphology, function, and evolution of liverwort scales" /><published>2024-12-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/liverwort-scales</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/liverwort-scales"><![CDATA[<p>Complex thalloid liverworts occurr are cosmopolitan plants. Although they are commonly thought to occurr in wet environments, they also occurr in seasonal and dry environments. While doing fieldwork across California, I became interested in the “rolling up” mechanism that some xerophytic complex thalloid liverworts display.</p>

<p>When dessicated, species like <em>Calasterella californica</em>, <em>Targionia hypophylla</em>, and <em>Reboulia hemisphaerica</em> thalli are surounded by its ventral scales. Interestingly, the ventral scales of all these species are red, a color that is commonly associated with UV-protective pigments.</p>

<p>During 2023-2024, I worked with two undergraduate researchers—Atra Shahryari and Riya Jain—testing the idea that the scales of <em>C. californica</em> protect the dessicated thalli against excess UV radiation. This research was recently published in Madroño, you can read the paper <a href="https://bioone.org/journals/madroño/volume-71/issue-4/0024-9637-71.4.145/UNVEILING-NATURES-SUNSCREEN--THE-POTENTIAL-ROLE-OF-LIVERWORT-SCALES/10.3120/0024-9637-71.4.145.short">HERE</a>.</p>

<p><img src="images/research/wet_dry.png" alt="Dry_Wet" width="550" />
<em>Calsterella californica hydrated (left) and dry (right). When the liverwort is hydrated, the scales are hidden between the thallus and the soil. The yellow arrows point to some scales that become exposed when the thallus is dried.</em></p>

<h3 id="ongoing-and-future-work">Ongoing and future work</h3>

<p>Our work with Calasterella californica suggests that the red ventral scales of liverworts that roll up might play an important role in liverwort adaptation to dry and exposed environments. In collaboration with <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/John-Mclaughlin-34">John McLaughlin</a>, we are working on documenting scale morphology across the family Aytoniaceae, and how it realtes to the ‘rolling up’ strategy.</p>

<p>Some of the questions that I am planning to address in the future are: what is the developmental origin of ventral scales? How do scale-morphology relates to scale function across complex thalloid liverworts? Is there a correlation between scale morphology, the ‘rolling-up’ strategy, and the environment that different lineages of liverworts occur in?</p>]]></content><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Complex thalloid liverworts occurr are cosmopolitan plants. Although they are commonly thought to occurr in wet environments, they also occurr in seasonal and dry environments. While doing fieldwork across California, I became interested in the “rolling up” mechanism that some xerophytic complex thalloid liverworts display.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/dry_liver.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/dry_liver.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Spatial phylogenetics: how lineages are distributed in geographic space</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/spa_phy" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Spatial phylogenetics: how lineages are distributed in geographic space" /><published>2024-12-04T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-04T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/spa_phy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/spa_phy"><![CDATA[<p>Spatial phylogenetics is an approach that studies the distribution of lineages across space. For this, we draw on the available genetic and collection data to 1) build phylogenies, and 2) characterize de distribution of taxa, to then study what lineages are represented across geographic space.</p>

<p>Since phylogenetic diversity is a good proxy for many important diversity traits (e.g. morphological and functional diversity), I am particularly interested in the conservation applications of this approach.</p>

<p>We recently used the spatial phylogenetics approach for California bryophytes. In this project we were interested in contrasting the byophyte phylogenetic diversity patterns, to the well known patterns of vascular plants. Furthermore, we present a methodological modification that allows to maximize the information obtained by species distribution models, and that we believe is an improvement on the treatment of information. You can read the preprint of this work <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2024.12.16.628580v1.abstract">HERE</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Spatial phylogenetics is an approach that studies the distribution of lineages across space. For this, we draw on the available genetic and collection data to 1) build phylogenies, and 2) characterize de distribution of taxa, to then study what lineages are represented across geographic space.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/cali_bryo.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/cali_bryo.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">PAw GeoSSE: a paleogreographically aware GeoSSE model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/paw" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="PAw GeoSSE: a paleogreographically aware GeoSSE model" /><published>2024-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/paw</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/paw"><![CDATA[<p>Phylogenetic biogeographers have understood range evolution as an historic process. As such, they have modeled the evolution of range as a character in an attribute of lineages that changes through time, using the character evolution machinery. Nevertheless, range evolution has been long recognized to have specific attributes that separate it from other chracters. For example, it is well known from a biological perspective that changes in the range or lineages are often associated with speciation events (e.g. allopatric speciation or jump dispersal). During my dissertation, I became interested in studying the evolution of the range in the family Aytoniaceae.</p>

<p>Studying ancient and widespread lineages exharcebates the likelihood of unobserved speciation events since more time has passed and thus the chances of lineages going extinct is higher. Not accounting for this possibility will potentially bias our estimates of the parameteres associated with range evolution. The GeoSSE machinery, while originally developped as a way to account for the effect that areas might have on diversification rates, provides a modelling framework where we can account for the probability of biogeographic evolution to be associated with missing speciation events as we model the diversification process in association with range evolution.</p>

<p>Furthermore, older lineages have experienced more continental configurations through time, thus, it is important to account for these changes when reconstructing widescale range evolution. By implementing a paleogeographically aware (Paw) geoSSE +J model, I studied the range evolution of Aytoniaceae liverworts and compared the effect of distance on liverwort anagenetic and cladogenetic dispersal events.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Phylogenetic biogeographers have understood range evolution as an historic process. As such, they have modeled the evolution of range as a character in an attribute of lineages that changes through time, using the character evolution machinery. Nevertheless, range evolution has been long recognized to have specific attributes that separate it from other chracters. For example, it is well known from a biological perspective that changes in the range or lineages are often associated with speciation events (e.g. allopatric speciation or jump dispersal). During my dissertation, I became interested in studying the evolution of the range in the family Aytoniaceae.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/areas_present.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/areas_present.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Divergence-time estimation using a FBD model and treating fossils as tips</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/TED" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Divergence-time estimation using a FBD model and treating fossils as tips" /><published>2024-12-02T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-02T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/TED</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/TED"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/seed_1.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/seed_1.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">A genomic approach to understand the genetic diversity and population structure of a liverwort species</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/Ccal" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A genomic approach to understand the genetic diversity and population structure of a liverwort species" /><published>2024-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/Ccal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/Ccal"><![CDATA[<p>As part of the California state wide <a href="https://www.ccgproject.org">CCGP project</a> (California Conservation Genomics Project), I have been studying the complex thalloid liverwort <em>Calasterella californica</em> for the past three years.</p>

<p><em>Calasterella californica</em> is a liverwort in the family Aytoniaceae that occurrs in the West Coast of Northamerica, extending from the southern part of Oregon to the North of Baja California. In California, it is one of the most common liverworts, occurring in a wide range of ecosystems, for example from temperate redwood forests to dry deserts.</p>

<p>Due to its importance in California ecosystems, this species was selected as one of the study species in the CCGP project, which aims to understand genetic diversity patterns across California and across a wide range of organisms. While contributing to this project, we aimed to understand some specific question about this species. How is the genetic diversity of this species distributed in space? How is the diversity structure in the context of the complex geology of California? Is this named species really a single clade or are there evolutionary differentiated units?</p>

<h3 id="a-reference-genome-for-c-californica">A reference genome for <em>C. californica</em></h3>
<p>In order to conduct genomic scale studies we need reference genomes. Thus, we constructed a <em>de novo</em> reference genome for <em>C. californica</em>.For this, we grew tissue in vitro from field-colected spores using high quality long-read sequencing. The genome is now a genomic resource publicly available. For more information, <a href="https://academic.oup.com/jhered/advance-article/doi/10.1093/jhered/esae065/7879539">check our publication</a>.</p>

<h3 id="genetic-diversity-across-the-geographic-space">Genetic diversity across the geographic space</h3>

<p>Liverworts disperse by spores. In comparison to the majority of seeds spores are small and thus are thought to disperse to longer distances. While large ranges are common among liverworts, the spread of the environments in which <em>C. californica</em> occurs raises the question of to what extent the populatios of these species mantain gene flow, and wether or not there is evidence of local adaptation. For this, we used a genomic approachh to characterize the genetic diversity of this species across its geographic range.</p>

<p>Our results suggest a clear pattern of genetic structure that follows a geographic differentiation. In Central and Northern California, there is a genetic divergence between coastal and mountain populations. There is a third region with genetically differentiated individuals occurring towards the Southeast of the state in the Sonora desert region. Southern California samples are characterized by displaying a mix of genetic markers of the other three well differentiated regions. Ongoing work is focused on further analyses to explore mechanistic explanations for this pattern.</p>

<p><img src="images/research/structure.png" alt="gen_pop" width="550" />
<em>Calasterella californica</em> genetic structure across its geographic range.</p>]]></content><author><name>Ixchel S. González Ramírez</name></author><category term="research" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As part of the California state wide CCGP project (California Conservation Genomics Project), I have been studying the complex thalloid liverwort Calasterella californica for the past three years.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/Calasterella.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/Calasterella.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>