<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
	<channel>
		<title>Ixchel González Ramírez</title>
		<description>My academic webpage</description>
		<link></link>
		<atom:link href="/rss-feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
		
			<item>
				<title>A California Native Plant Society public hike: learning little plants among the redwoods</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;*Main post picture by Sunit Mody&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/CNPS_bryowalk</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/CNPS_bryowalk</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>New pre-print on the microbiome of C. californica</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with my friend and colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://michaelsongagradstudent.github.io&quot;&gt;Mick Song&lt;/a&gt;, we used the sequencing of field collected liverworts in the species &lt;em&gt;C. californica&lt;/em&gt; to study their associated microbiome. In this fun collaboration we learned that there is a core group of bacteria that is present across all samples. We also found that the differences observed in the composition is better explained by the genetics of the host liverwort. All of this opens interesting question about the role that liverworts might play in a selection mechanism of the bacteria in their microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/microbiome</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/microbiome</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Morphology, function, and evolution of liverwort scales</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Complex thalloid liverworts occurr are cosmopolitan plants. Although they are commonly thought to occurr in wet environments, they also occurr in seasonal and dry environments. While doing fieldwork across California, I became interested in the “rolling up” mechanism that some xerophytic complex thalloid liverworts display.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/liverwort-scales</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/liverwort-scales</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Spatial phylogenetics: how lineages are distributed in geographic space</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Spatial phylogenetics is an approach that studies the distribution of lineages across space. For this, we draw on the available genetic and collection data to 1) build phylogenies, and 2) characterize de distribution of taxa, to then study what lineages are represented across geographic space.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/spa_phy</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/spa_phy</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>PAw GeoSSE: a paleogreographically aware GeoSSE model</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;Phylogenetic biogeographers have understood range evolution as an historic process. As such, they have modeled the evolution of range as a character in an attribute of lineages that changes through time, using the character evolution machinery. Nevertheless, range evolution has been long recognized to have specific attributes that separate it from other chracters. For example, it is well known from a biological perspective that changes in the range or lineages are often associated with speciation events (e.g. allopatric speciation or jump dispersal). During my dissertation, I became interested in studying the evolution of the range in the family Aytoniaceae.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/paw</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/paw</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>Divergence-time estimation using a FBD model and treating fossils as tips</title>
				
				
					<description>
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/TED</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/TED</guid>
			</item>
		
			<item>
				<title>A genomic approach to understand the genetic diversity and population structure of a liverwort species</title>
				
				
					<description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the California state wide &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ccgproject.org&quot;&gt;CCGP project&lt;/a&gt; (California Conservation Genomics Project), I have been studying the complex thalloid liverwort &lt;em&gt;Calasterella californica&lt;/em&gt; for the past three years.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
				
				<pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
				<link>http://localhost:4000/Ccal</link>
				<guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/Ccal</guid>
			</item>
		
	</channel>
</rss>
